In the last lecture we learn how to use nested routes.
Son derste i ie gemi rotalarn nasl kullanlacan reneceiz.
Now you might have noticed one thing maybe even earlier, when we are on a given post and we click on
Belirli bir yayn zerindeyken imdi belki daha erken bir ey fark etmi olabilirsiniz
a different post, we don't actually load that though you can see in the URL that the ID changes.
ve baka bir postaya tklarsak, aslnda borcu yklemediimiz halde Kimlii deitiinde R L'de grebilirsiniz.
So it is registering the click but it isn't loading the new component.
Dolaysyla tklamay kaydediyor ancak yeni bileeni yklemiyor.
Now the reason for this is that react router behind the scenes doesn't replace the component all the
imdi bunun nedeni, sahnelerin arkasndaki l yeniden aktr ynlendiricinin her zaman bileenin yerini
time.
almas deil.
If you're loading a component on which you're already on, like we are here, it won't re-render the
olduunuz gibi bir bileeni yklyorsak buradayz, tm bileeni gerekten oluturmayacaktr ve bu
whole component and therefore for the full post, componentDidMount isn't executed again, because why
nedenle tam yaz bileeni iin yeniden mount yaplmad, nk bunu neden yapard.
would it do that?
Halihazrda zerinde
The component itself didn't change it would be very inefficient to unmount it and remount it.
Kendisinin zd paralamay deitirmeyin, paralamay kaldrmak ve yeniden balamak ok verimsiz olurdu.
So since componentsDidMount isn't executed again though, we're not reaching out to the web again.
Komponentlerden beri yeniden montaj yaplmad, ancak tekrar web'e ulaamayacaz.
So to fix this what we should do is we should also implement componentDidUpdate to handle this case
Bunu dzeltmek iin yapmamz gereken ey, gncelleme yaplaca iin yeniden altrlaca iin bu
because did update will be executed again.
davay ilemek iin gncelleme bileenini de uygulamamzdr.
And I will add a new method, loadData convenience method which will simply hold my old code here where
yk veri kolayl yntemi ekleyeceim, nk imdi bunu hem bileen montajnda hem de bileen olarak armak
I reach out to the web and load my data because now I want to call this both in componentDidMount and
istiyorum, bu yk verileri bu her iki yaam dngs kancasnda da arlmal, bylece
componentDidUpdate. So this loadData will be called in both lifecycle hooks so that I'm prepared
hem ilk kez hem de bu tekli yk yklendi ve ikinci kez hazrlandm.
both for the first time this single post gets loaded and the second time.
Ve eski kodu burada web'e uzatacam ve verilerimi ykleyecek yeni bir yntem
Now however you see by the console log already, we have an infinite loop
Ancak imdi konsol gnlne gre sonsuz bir dngye zaten sahibiz.
so this is not the perfect solution,
Dolaysyla bu mkemmel bir zm deildir.
I click on a link here and it keeps on loading again.
Buraya bir balanty tklyorum ve tekrar yklemeye devam ediyor.
So definitely not what we want to do, what's wrong with our current setup here?
Kesin olarak burada mevcut kurulumumuzdaki yanl olan yapmak istemediimiz ey.
Well it's our check in loadData, we're checking if our id changed and we're checking for
Peki, yk verilerimizdeki eklerimiz, fikrimizin deiip deimediini kontrol ediyor ve bu doru kimlii kontrol
this.props.id.
ediyoruz.
Now just as everywhere else here, this needs to be this.props.match.params.id, this.props.id will
her yerde olduu gibi bu pervanenin ei olmas gerekiyor Perrin'in kimlii bu pervanenin kimlii asla belirlenmeyecek.
never be set.
imdi de burada
So we had the same infinite loop problem we had in the HTTP section because our check here wasn't working
Dolaysyla, HD blmnde sahip olduumuz ayn sonsuz dng sorunumuz vard nk eklerimiz artk
anymore and we not only need to update this here, we need to update it everywhere in this component where
almyordu ve biz sadece bunu gncellememiz gerekmiyor; bunu her yerde gncellememiz gerekiyor ve
we reference this.props.id. Of course also here, otherwise deleting would never work,
tabii ki bu pervanenin Kimliini de referans aldmz bileen olarak da te silmenin asla ie yaramayaca nedeni.
and of course also down here where we check if the ID is set.
Ve tabii ki burada kimlii ayarlanm olup olmadn kontrol ettiimiz yer.
Now with all these changes in place, it would still not work because the ID we're retrieving from the
imdi yerinde olan bu deiikliklerle birlikte, yine de ie yaramayacakt, nk
route params is actually going to be a string.
kimlii gururlu ailelerden almak aslnda bir dize olacakt.
Now here we're checking for type equality too and the id stored in the loaded post actually is a number.
imdi burada ykl postta depolanan anti-ID eitlii iin bir numara olduunu kontrol ediyoruz.
So we either have to convert these string IDs to a number or simply turn this into a check where we just
Dolaysyla ya E-dize kimlii kelimesini bir numaraya almal ya da bunu sadece bir onay iaretine
check for the value.
evirmeliyiz veya deeri kontrol etmeliyiz.
Now if we just check just for the value and we click a post,
imdi sadece deeri kontrol edip bir yazy tklarsak.
now you see it's not loading all the time,
Artk her zaman yklenmediini gryorsun.
instead it only loads once but it correctly updates it when we switch to post.
Bunun yerine, yalnzca bir kez ykler, ancak yayna getiimizde onu dzgn ekilde gnceller.
Again the alternative would be to leave the type quality check but to convert this into a number by
Yine alternatif, yazarak kalite kontrolnden vazgemek ama bunun nne bir art
adding a plus in front of it, for example.
ekleyerek bir sayya dntrmek olacaktr.
Now again if I click on a post, we load it, we load it only once,
imdi yklediimiz bir postay tklarsak, yalnzca bir kez yklenir.
we don't enter the infinite loop.
Sonsuz dngye girmiyoruz.
This is an important fix to the full post component in general that we use match.params.id all over
Genel post bileeninin nemli bir dzeltmesi, bileen genelinde Perens ID
in the component and it's also important to understand that you need to handle changes in componentDidUpdate
elemesini kullandmz ve bileendeki deiiklikleri gerekletirmeniz gerektiini anlamak da nemlidir.
if the post component or if component in general is already loaded through routing because the
DB post bileenini mi yoksa genel olarak bileen ynlendirmeye yklendiyse gncelleme mi yaptnz, nk ynlendirici
router will not unmount the old one and mount the same one again with different data,
eskisinin balantsn kesmeyecek ve ayn veriyi farkl verilerle yeniden balamayacaktr.
it will reuse the old one and just adjust the route parameter,
Eski rotay tekrar kullanacak ve sadece rota parametresini ayarlayacaktr.
it's your job to react to this new parameter and you can react to that in componentDidUpdate which
Bu yeni parametreye tepki gstermek sizin iinizdir ve sahada deiiklik olmas nedeniyle arlabilecek bu
will be called because the props changed.
gncelleme bileenine tepki verebilirsiniz.
You receive a new props with a new match object with a new params object with the new ID,
Yeni kimlie sahip yeni bir ebeveyn nesnesine sahip yeni bir eleme nesnesine sahip yeni bir kulplu alrsnz.
this is what's happening here,
Burada olan bitti.
this is what we're taking advantage of
Yararladmz eyi yapar.
and this is important to understand
Ve anlamak nemlidir.
when working with nested routes.
ie gemi rotalarla alrken.